Meditation NNP O
Park NNP O
is VBZ O
a DT O
big JJ O
movie NN O
about IN O
a DT O
tiny JJ O
woman NN O
. . O

Written VBN O
and CC O
directed VBN O
by IN O
Canadian JJ O
indie NN O
filmmaker NN O
Mina NNP B-PERSON
Shum NNP I-PERSON
, , O
the DT O
new JJ O
drama NN O
follows VBZ O
a DT O
Chinese JJ O
immigrant JJ O
grandma NN O
named VBN O
Maria NNP B-PERSON
who WP O
is VBZ O
stunned JJ O
to TO O
discover VB O
her PRP$ O
husband NN O
's POS O
infidelity NN O
. . O

The DT O
reassuring JJ O
idyll NN O
of IN O
her PRP$ O
40-year CD O
marriage NN O
breaks NNS O
, , O
and CC O
she PRP O
sets VBZ O
out RP O
to TO O
discover VB O
what WP O
more RBR O
she PRP O
might MD O
want VB O
from IN O
this DT O
life NN O
. . O

With IN O
an DT O
epic JJ O
score NN O
and CC O
lush JJ O
, , O
lingering VBG O
camera NN O
work NN O
, , O
it PRP O
's VBZ O
a DT O
self NN O
- HYPH O
assured VBN O
film NN O
- HYPH O
confident JJ O
, , O
a DT O
little JJ O
heartbreaking JJ O
and CC O
very RB O
funny JJ O
. . O

Immigrant JJ O
stories NNS O
do VBP O
n't RB O
often RB O
get VB O
the DT O
Oscar NNP B-PERSON
- HYPH O
baiting VBG O
budgets NNS O
of IN O
Hollywood NNP B-GPE
, , O
but CC O
that DT O
did VBD O
n't RB O
stop VB O
Shum NNP O
from IN O
making VBG O
hers PRP O
look VB O
like IN O
it PRP O
did VBD O
. . O

In IN O
an DT O
interview NN O
during IN O
this DT B-DATE
past JJ I-DATE
fall NN I-DATE
's POS I-DATE
Toronto NNP O
International NNP O
Film NNP O
Festival NNP O
, , O
Shum NNP B-ORGANIZATION
said VBD O
her PRP$ O
lead JJ O
character NN O
deserved VBD O
Champagne NNP B-PERSON
treatment NN O
despite IN O
the DT O
film NN O
's POS O
beer NN O
budget NN O
. . O

" `` O
I PRP O
wanted VBD O
to TO O
make VB O
a DT O
Marvel NNP O
movie NN O
about IN O
Maria NNP B-GPE
, , O
" '' O
Shum NNP O
says VBZ O
, , O
complete JJ O
with IN O
" `` O
beautiful JJ O
production NN O
design NN O
, , O
wonderful JJ O
shots NNS O
, , O
big JJ O
production NN O
value NN O
and CC O
, , O
yet RB O
, , O
18 CD B-DATE
days NNS I-DATE
and CC O
limited JJ O
resources NNS O
. . O
" '' O

" `` O
There EX O
are VBP O
a DT O
lot NN O
of IN O
films NNS O
where WRB O
it PRP O
's VBZ O
like UH O
, , O
' '' O
Okay UH O
, , O
it PRP O
's VBZ O
the DT O
marginalized JJ O
hero NN O
, , O
so CC O
I PRP O
'm VBP O
just RB O
going VBG O
to TO O
be VB O
over RB O
here RB O
with IN O
my PRP$ O
low JJ O
- HYPH O
budget NN O
camera NN O
, , O
' '' O
" '' O
adds VBZ O
the DT O
director NN O
, , O
who WP O
opted VBD O
to TO O
translate VB O
the DT O
rich JJ O
hues NNS O
of IN O
Maria NNP B-GPE
's POS O
inner JJ O
life NN O
with IN O
equally RB O
capacious JJ O
cinematography NN O
. . O

Maria NNP B-GPE
, , O
played VBD O
with IN O
total JJ O
charm NN O
by IN O
Pei NNP B-ORGANIZATION
- HYPH I-ORGANIZATION
Pei NNP I-ORGANIZATION
Cheng NNP I-ORGANIZATION
( -LRB- O
Crouching NNP O
Tiger NNP O
, , O
Hidden NNP O
Dragon NNP O
) -RRB- O
, , O
is VBZ O
the DT O
still JJ O
point NN O
of IN O
her PRP$ O
family NN O
's POS O
turning VBG O
world NN O
, , O
although IN O
she PRP O
rarely RB O
gets VBZ O
the DT O
credit NN O
for IN O
being VBG O
so RB O
. . O

Puttering VBG O
around IN O
her PRP$ O
Vancouver NNP B-GPE
home NN O
, , O
cooking NN O
and CC O
cleaning NN O
, , O
she PRP O
waits VBZ O
on IN O
her PRP$ O
husband NN O
( -LRB- O
Tzi NNP B-ORGANIZATION
Ma NNP I-ORGANIZATION
, , O
of IN O
Arrival NNP B-PERSON
) -RRB- O
and CC O
tries VBZ O
to TO O
please VB O
her PRP$ O
grown JJ O
daughter NN O
- HYPH O
Sandra NNP O
Oh UH O
( -LRB- O
Grey NNP B-PERSON
's POS O
Anatomy NNP O
) -RRB- O
in IN O
the DT O
role NN O
of IN O
Ava NNP B-PERSON
. . O

When WRB O
Maria NNP B-PERSON
fishes VBZ O
a DT O
lacy NN O
thong NN O
, , O
decidedly RB O
not RB O
hers PRP O
, , O
out IN O
of IN O
her PRP$ O
husband NN O
's POS O
pants NNS O
pocket NN O
, , O
she PRP O
begins VBZ O
to TO O
question VB O
her PRP$ O
four CD B-DATE
decades NNS I-DATE
of IN O
sacrifice NN O
. . O

After IN O
the DT O
death NN O
of IN O
her PRP$ O
own JJ O
father NN O
nine CD B-DATE
years NNS I-DATE
ago RB I-DATE
, , O
Shum NNP B-ORGANIZATION
watched VBD O
as IN O
her PRP$ O
mother NN O
" '' O
blossomed VBD O
in IN O
a DT O
different JJ O
way NN O
, , O
" '' O
suddenly RB O
her PRP$ O
own JJ O
person NN O
without IN O
children NNS O
or CC O
a DT O
husband NN O
to TO O
tend VB O
to TO O
. . O

" `` O
There EX O
's VBZ O
something NN O
about IN O
the DT O
lingering VBG O
history NN O
of IN O
the DT O
patriarch NN O
I PRP O
thought VBD O
was VBD O
interesting JJ O
, , O
" '' O
she PRP O
says VBZ O
. . O

The DT O
charisma NN O
and CC O
delight NN O
of IN O
Meditation NNP O
Park NNP O
builds VBZ O
slowly RB O
as IN O
the DT O
viewer NN O
acclimatizes VBZ O
to IN O
Maria NNP B-PERSON
's POS O
shy JJ O
and CC O
gentle JJ O
rhythms NNS O
. . O

Although IN O
she PRP O
initially RB O
takes VBZ O
the DT O
stereotypical JJ O
shape NN O
of IN O
a DT O
doting VBG O
immigrant JJ O
mom NN O
and CC O
wife NN O
, , O
her PRP$ O
character NN O
does VBZ O
n't RB O
remain VB O
stuck JJ O
there RB O
. . O

" `` O
Our PRP$ O
understanding NN O
of IN O
what WP O
a DT O
Chinese JJ O
immigrant JJ O
woman NN O
would MD O
be VB O
is VBZ O
exactly RB O
what WP O
we PRP O
see VBP O
at IN O
the DT O
beginning NN O
of IN O
the DT O
film NN O
, , O
" '' O
Shum NNP O
says VBZ O
. . O

" `` O
Then RB O
, , O
it PRP O
gets VBZ O
broken VBN O
down RP O
, , O
and CC O
so RB O
our PRP$ O
expectations NNS O
as IN O
an DT O
audience NN O
get VBP O
turned VBN O
on RP O
their PRP$ O
head NN O
- : O
and CC O
then RB O
we PRP O
're VBP O
off IN O
to IN O
the DT O
races NNS O
. . O

If IN O
we PRP O
can MD O
identify VB O
her PRP O
as IN O
a DT O
hero NN O
, , O
then RB O
ca MD O
n't RB O
we PRP O
all DT O
be VB O
heroes NNS O
? . O
" '' O

It PRP O
was VBD O
at IN O
TIFF NNP B-ORGANIZATION
in IN O
1994 CD B-DATE
where WRB O
Shum NNP B-ORGANIZATION
made VBD O
her PRP$ O
directorial JJ O
debut NN O
with IN O
Double JJ O
Happiness NN O
- : O
another DT O
story NN O
of IN O
immigrant JJ O
family NN O
life NN O
, , O
which WDT O
cast VBD O
Oh UH O
in IN O
the DT O
actor NN O
's POS O
first JJ O
lead JJ O
role NN O
. . O

Oh UH O
then RB O
appeared VBD O
in IN O
Shum NNP B-ORGANIZATION
's POS I-ORGANIZATION
Long NNP I-ORGANIZATION
Life NNP I-ORGANIZATION
, , I-ORGANIZATION
Happiness NNP I-ORGANIZATION
& CC I-ORGANIZATION
Prosperity NNP I-ORGANIZATION
( -LRB- O
2002 CD B-DATE
) -RRB- O
and CC O
happily RB O
signed VBN O
on RP O
for IN O
this DT O
third JJ O
project NN O
. . O

" `` O
It PRP O
's VBZ O
funny JJ O
because IN O
when WRB O
I PRP O
was VBD O
going VBG O
on IN O
the DT O
press NN O
tour NN O
with IN O
Double JJ O
Happiness NNP O
, , O
I PRP O
was VBD O
always RB O
saying VBG O
, , O
' `` O
I PRP O
'm VBP O
curious JJ O
what WP O
I PRP O
'm VBP O
going VBG O
to TO O
be VB O
making VBG O
in IN O
20 CD B-DATE
years NNS I-DATE
, , O
' '' O
so RB O
here RB O
we PRP O
are VBP O
, , O
" '' O
Shum NNP B-ORGANIZATION
says VBZ O
with IN O
a DT O
smile NN O
. . O

The DT O
difference NN O
between IN O
then RB O
and CC O
now RB O
? . O

" `` O
We PRP O
're VBP O
all DT O
more RBR O
experienced JJ O
. . O

That DT O
's VBZ O
definitely RB O
what WP O
I PRP O
noticed VBD O
. . O

Instead RB O
of IN O
needing VBG O
a DT O
second JJ O
take NN O
because IN O
of IN O
something NN O
, , O
we PRP O
worked VBD O
it PRP O
out RP O
before IN O
the DT O
first JJ O
take NN O
happened VBN O
. . O
" '' O

In IN O
addition NN O
to IN O
various JJ O
short JJ O
films NNS O
and CC O
television NN O
credits NNS O
, , O
Shum NNP B-ORGANIZATION
also RB O
directed VBD O
the DT O
feature NN O
Drive NN O
, , O
She PRP O
Said VBD B-PERSON
( -LRB- O
1997 CD B-DATE
) -RRB- O
and CC O
a DT O
National NNP B-ORGANIZATION
Film NNP I-ORGANIZATION
Board NNP I-ORGANIZATION
documentary NN O
about IN O
the DT O
Sir NNP O
George NNP B-PERSON
Williams NNP I-PERSON
affair NN O
called VBD O
Ninth NNP B-ORGANIZATION
Floor NNP I-ORGANIZATION
( -LRB- O
2015 CD B-DATE
) -RRB- O
. . O

Shum NNP O
and CC O
the DT O
cast NN O
got VBD O
a DT O
brief JJ O
window NN O
for IN O
rehearsals NNS O
before IN O
filming VBG O
and CC O
they PRP O
used VBD O
the DT O
time NN O
to TO O
" `` O
improvise VB O
around IN O
the DT O
movie NN O
. . O
" '' O

They PRP O
" `` O
never RB O
looked VBD O
at IN O
the DT O
script NN O
when WRB O
rehearsing VBG O
, , O
" '' O
which WDT O
is VBZ O
a DT O
process NN O
that WDT O
Shum NNP O
prefers NNS O
, , O
and CC O
instead RB O
they PRP O
developed VBD O
the DT O
family NN O
dynamics NNS O
that WDT O
would MD O
come VB O
to TO O
animate VB O
the DT O
film NN O
. . O

The DT O
cast NN O
of IN O
Meditation NNP O
Park NNP O
have VBP O
an DT O
undeniable JJ O
chemistry NN O
that WDT O
makes VBZ O
their PRP$ O
kinship NN O
all PDT O
the DT O
more RBR O
believable JJ O
- : O
but CC O
it PRP O
helps VBZ O
that IN O
they PRP O
have VBP O
history NN O
. . O

" `` O
Tzi NNP B-ORGANIZATION
Ma NNP I-ORGANIZATION
and CC O
Sandra NNP B-PERSON
worked VBD O
together RB O
on IN O
Grey NNP B-ORGANIZATION
's POS I-ORGANIZATION
Anatomy NNP I-ORGANIZATION
, , O
" '' O
Shum NNP O
explains VBZ O
, , O
and CC O
" `` O
Tzi NNP O
had VBD O
a DT O
crush NN O
on IN O
Pei NNP B-ORGANIZATION
- HYPH I-ORGANIZATION
Pei NNP I-ORGANIZATION
when WRB O
she PRP O
was VBD O
younger JJR O
. . O
" '' O

Everyone NN O
's POS O
impressive JJ O
reputation NN O
preceded VBD O
them PRP O
, , O
and CC O
the DT O
actors NNS O
shared VBD O
" `` O
a DT O
real JJ O
desire NN O
to TO O
tell VB O
this DT O
story NN O
. . O
" '' O

When WRB O
Shum NNP O
flew VBD O
to IN O
Shanghai NNP B-GPE
two CD B-DATE
years NNS I-DATE
before IN O
filming VBG O
to TO O
meet VB O
Pei NNP O
- HYPH O
Pei NNP O
in IN O
person NN O
, , O
the DT O
actor NN O
told VBD O
her PRP O
she PRP O
'd MD O
never RB O
seen VBN O
a DT O
story NN O
quite RB O
like IN O
this DT O
one NN O
before RB O
, , O
and CC O
she PRP O
was VBD O
thrilled VBN O
at IN O
its PRP$ O
prospect NN O
. . O

Shum NNP O
was VBD O
born VBN O
in IN O
Hong NNP B-GPE
Kong NNP I-GPE
and CC O
came VBD O
to IN O
Vancouver NNP B-GPE
with IN O
her PRP$ O
family NN O
as IN O
a DT O
young JJ O
child NN O
. . O

The DT O
story NN O
of IN O
Meditation NNP O
Park NNP O
is VBZ O
fiction NN O
, , O
but CC O
its PRP$ O
themes NNS O
resonate VBP O
with IN O
the DT O
first JJ O
generation NN O
of IN O
Chinese JJ O
immigrant JJ O
women NNS O
that WDT O
Shum NNP B-ORGANIZATION
knows VBZ O
. . O

" `` O
In IN O
Chinese JJ O
culture NN O
, , O
we PRP O
had VBD O
concubines NNS O
in IN O
the DT O
old JJ O
days NNS O
with IN O
lords NNS O
and CC O
emperors NNS O
, , O
and CC O
there EX O
's VBZ O
always RB O
been VBN O
this DT O
, , O
' '' O
he PRP O
might MD O
have VB O
a DT O
girlfriend NN O
, , O
' '' O
thing NN O
, , O
" '' O
Shum NNP O
explains VBZ O
. . O

" `` O
Like UH O
, , O
my PRP$ O
mother NN O
always RB O
said VBD O
to IN O
me PRP O
that IN O
the DT O
best JJS O
thing NN O
my PRP$ O
father NN O
did VBD O
was VBD O
never RB O
cheat VB O
. . O

That DT O
was VBD O
the DT O
most RBS O
important JJ O
thing NN O
. . O

Not RB O
that IN O
he PRP O
raised VBD O
a DT O
family NN O
, , O
but CC O
that IN O
he PRP O
stayed VBD O
. . O
" '' O

Astute VB B-GPE
to IN O
both DT O
generational JJ O
and CC O
cultural JJ O
differences NNS O
, , O
Shum NNP O
adds VBZ O
: : O
" `` O
I PRP O
mean VBP O
infidelity NN O
happens VBZ O
everywhere RB O
, , O
but CC O
if IN O
it PRP O
happened VBD O
to IN O
you PRP O
or CC O
me PRP O
, , O
we PRP O
'd MD O
talk VB O
- HYPH O
therapy NN O
it PRP O
out RP O
, , O
we PRP O
'd MD O
get VB O
a DT O
divorce NN O
, , O
we PRP O
'd MD O
Tinder VB O
date NN O
, , O
we PRP O
'd MD O
find VB O
a DT O
new JJ O
boyfriend NN O
! . O

There EX O
's VBZ O
so RB O
much JJ O
empowerment NN O
for IN O
the DT O
women NNS O
in IN O
my PRP$ O
world NN O
, , O
in IN O
my PRP$ O
generation NN O
, , O
that IN O
it PRP O
's VBZ O
almost RB O
shocking JJ O
to TO O
know VB O
that IN O
someone NN O
would MD O
feel VB O
so RB O
powerless JJ O
. . O
" '' O

There EX O
was VBD O
something NN O
else RB O
Shum NNP B-ORGANIZATION
's POS I-ORGANIZATION
mother NN O
said VBD O
to IN O
her PRP O
that IN O
the DT O
director NN O
credits VBZ O
as IN O
the DT O
script NN O
's POS O
initial JJ O
spark NN O
. . O

" `` O
She PRP O
said VBD O
to IN O
me PRP O
in IN O
Cantonese NNP O
about IN O
a DT O
friend NN O
that IN O
' '' O
the DT O
cat NN O
has VBZ O
got VBN O
a DT O
new JJ O
fish NN O
, , O
' '' O
and CC O
I PRP O
did VBD O
n't RB O
know VB O
what WP O
we PRP O
were VBD O
talking VBG O
about IN O
, , O
" '' O
Shum NNP O
says VBZ O
. . O

When WRB O
her PRP$ O
mom NN O
explained VBD O
that IN O
" `` O
so RB O
- HYPH O
and CC O
- HYPH O
so RB O
has VBZ O
got VBN O
a DT O
new JJ O
lover NN O
, , O
" `` O
Shum NNP O
delighted VBD O
in IN O
the DT O
peculiar JJ O
euphemism NN O
. . O

" `` O
You PRP O
call VBP O
it PRP O
a DT O
' `` O
cat NN O
has VBZ O
got VBN O
a DT O
new JJ O
fish NN O
? . O
' '' O

Oh UH O
my UH O
god UH O
, , O
I PRP O
love VBP O
being VBG O
Chinese JJ O
, , O
I PRP O
love VBP O
the DT O
Cantonese JJ O
language NN O
, , O
I PRP O
love VBP O
Chinese JJ O
women NNS O
. . O

And CC O
then RB O
the DT O
whole JJ O
story NN O
came VBD O
to IN O
me PRP O
. . O
" '' O

As IN O
for IN O
the DT O
film NN O
's POS O
title NN O
, , O
it PRP O
refers VBZ O
to IN O
the DT O
neighbourhood NN O
park NN O
that WDT O
separates VBZ O
Maria NNP B-PERSON
from IN O
, , O
and CC O
later RB O
connects VBZ O
her PRP O
to IN O
, , O
the DT O
community NN O
. . O

A DT O
motley JJ O
crew NN O
indeed RB O
, , O
Maria NNP B-PERSON
's POS O
neighbours NNS O
are VBP O
a DT O
gaggle NN O
of IN O
Chinese JJ O
women NNS O
hawking VBG O
illegal JJ O
parking NN O
spots NNS O
and CC O
a DT O
grief NN O
- HYPH O
stricken VBN O
white JJ O
man NN O
who WP O
encroaches VBZ O
on IN O
their PRP$ O
turf NN O
. . O

" `` O
Yeah UH O
, , O
it PRP O
's VBZ O
the DT O
park NN O
in IN O
the DT O
film NN O
, , O
but CC O
it PRP O
also RB O
refers VBZ O
to IN O
how WRB O
we PRP O
're VBP O
all DT O
in IN O
meditation NN O
park NN O
, , O
" '' O
Shum NNP O
says VBZ O
. . O

" `` O
We PRP O
all DT O
know VBP O
life NN O
is VBZ O
finite JJ O
. . O

We PRP O
're VBP O
all DT O
struggling VBG O
to TO O
find VB O
happiness NN O
, , O
we PRP O
're VBP O
all DT O
struggling VBG O
to TO O
find VB O
harmony NN O
with IN O
each DT O
other JJ O
. . O
" '' O

She PRP O
hopes VBZ O
that IN O
the DT O
film NN O
will MD O
serve VB O
as IN O
a DT O
keyhole NN O
into IN O
a DT O
community NN O
and CC O
age NN O
group NN O
that WDT O
our PRP$ O
culture NN O
does VBZ O
n't RB O
usually RB O
privilege JJ O
as IN O
heroes NNS O
. . O

In IN O
making VBG O
Meditation NNP O
Park NNP O
, , O
Shum NNP O
herself PRP O
found VBD O
a DT O
measure NN O
of IN O
harmony NN O
. . O

" `` O
I PRP O
had VBD O
written VBN O
a DT O
very RB O
big JJ O
Hollywood NNP B-GPE
film NN O
, , O
" '' O
she PRP O
said VBD O
, , O
which WDT O
after IN O
four CD B-DATE
years NNS I-DATE
of IN O
working VBG O
on RB O
, , O
did VBD O
n't RB O
end VB O
up RP O
happening VBG O
. . O

Then RB O
came VBD O
along IN O
the DT O
idea NN O
of IN O
a DT O
smaller JJR O
, , O
more RBR O
intimate JJ O
movie NN O
. . O

Writing VBG O
the DT O
script NN O
had VBD O
" `` O
never RB O
come VB O
easier JJR O
, , O
" '' O
Shum NNP O
says VBZ O
. . O

" `` O
In IN O
fact NN O
it PRP O
's VBZ O
bizarre JJ O
. . O

It PRP O
's VBZ O
once RB O
in IN O
a DT O
lifetime NN O
. . O

I PRP O
was VBD O
like UH O
, , O
' '' O
That DT O
was VBD O
magic JJ O
. . O
' '' O

" `` O
Meditation NNP O
Park NNP O
is VBZ O
now RB O
playing VBG O
in IN O
Toronto NNP B-GPE
and CC O
Vancouver NNP B-GPE
. . O

Credit NN O
: : O
Special JJ O
to IN O
The DT B-ORGANIZATION
Globe NNP I-ORGANIZATION
and CC I-ORGANIZATION
Mail NNP I-ORGANIZATION

